<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://adwaykanhere.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://adwaykanhere.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-06-13T18:17:37+00:00</updated><id>https://adwaykanhere.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><entry><title type="html">The story behind FarmPlus</title><link href="https://adwaykanhere.github.io/2025/06/01/farmplusstory.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The story behind FarmPlus"/><published>2025-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://adwaykanhere.github.io/2025/06/01/farmplusstory</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://adwaykanhere.github.io/2025/06/01/farmplusstory.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="wip">[WIP]</h1> <p>We all underestimate the importance of dairy in our lives. Our morning coffee, the cereal we grab for breakfast, the cream in our pasta sauces, and countless other foods we consume daily all depend on a reliable supply of fresh, high-quality milk. Yet most of us never stop to think about the complex systems and challenges that dairy farmers face to get that milk from farm to table.</p> <p>This is the story of how a casual evening conversation over chai led to FarmPlus, a dairy-tech startup that won first place at the 2022 Hopkins New Venture Challenge and was subsequently incubated at the JHU Spark Incubator. It’s a tale of recognizing opportunity in everyday problems, the power of interdisciplinary collaboration, and what happens when academic curiosity meets real-world impact.</p> <h2 id="the-evening-that-started-it-all">The Evening That Started It All</h2> <h2 id="the-problem-we-discovered">The Problem We Discovered</h2> <h2 id="building-the-solution">Building the Solution</h2> <h2 id="the-technology-stack">The Technology Stack</h2> <p>Our solution centered around a collar-mounted device that we designed to be both practical and affordable. Here’s how we approached the key technical challenges:</p> <p><strong>Hardware Design</strong>: We created a rugged, waterproof collar that housed multiple sensors—accelerometers for movement tracking, temperature sensors for health monitoring, and specialized algorithms to detect rumination patterns. The device was designed to last several years with minimal maintenance.</p> <p><strong>Connectivity</strong>: Rather than relying on expensive cellular connections, we implemented a mesh network system using long-range, low-power radio frequencies. This allowed data from individual cows to be collected at a central hub, even on large farms with limited infrastructure.</p> <p><strong>Data Analytics</strong>: We developed machine learning models that could identify patterns indicative of health issues, breeding readiness, and productivity optimization. The system learned from each farm’s specific conditions and herd characteristics, becoming more accurate over time.</p> <p><strong>User Interface</strong>: We designed a simple, intuitive dashboard that provided farmers with actionable insights without overwhelming them with data. Key alerts were prioritized, and the system could send notifications via text message or email when immediate attention was needed.</p> <h2 id="validation-and-early-wins">Validation and Early Wins</h2> <h2 id="the-incubator-experience">The Incubator Experience</h2> <p>Being selected for the JHU Spark Incubator was a game-changer. The program provided not just funding and workspace, but access to mentors, advisors, and a network of other entrepreneurs facing similar challenges.</p> <p>One of the most valuable aspects was the regular check-ins and milestone setting. As academics, we were used to long-term research projects with gradual progress. The startup world demanded rapid iteration and quick pivots based on market feedback.</p> <p>We learned to embrace failure as a learning opportunity. Our first hardware design, while technically sound, was overcomplicated and expensive to manufacture. Customer interviews revealed that farmers valued simplicity and reliability over advanced features they might never use.</p> <p>We pivoted our approach, simplifying the device while focusing on the features that provided the most value. This meant making hard decisions about what to include and what to leave out, but it ultimately led to a better product-market fit.</p> <h2 id="lessons-learned">Lessons Learned</h2> <p>The FarmPlus journey taught us several crucial lessons about entrepreneurship, technology development, and market validation:</p> <p><strong>Customer-Centric Design</strong>: No matter how elegant our technical solution was, it only mattered if it solved real problems for real customers in a way they were willing to pay for. Spending time on farms, talking to farmers, and observing their daily routines was more valuable than any amount of theoretical market research.</p> <p><strong>The Importance of Interdisciplinary Teams</strong>: Our backgrounds in biomedical engineering and business complemented each other perfectly. Neither of us could have built FarmPlus alone, but together we could tackle both the technical challenges and business development needs.</p> <p><strong>Iterative Development</strong>: The temptation in academic settings is to perfect something before showing it to the world. In startup land, getting feedback early and often—even on imperfect prototypes—led to better outcomes and faster progress.</p> <p><strong>Market Education</strong>: We underestimated how much work would be required to educate the market about the value of our solution. Many farmers were initially skeptical of technology, having been burned by previous “innovative” solutions that didn’t deliver on their promises.</p> <p><strong>Regulatory Considerations</strong>: While our device didn’t require FDA approval, we did need to consider various agricultural regulations and standards. This added complexity but also created barriers to entry that could protect us from competitors.</p> <h2 id="the-bigger-picture">The Bigger Picture</h2> <p>FarmPlus was more than just a business venture—it was our introduction to the intersection of technology and agriculture, a space with enormous potential for positive impact. Agriculture feeds the world, but it also faces unprecedented challenges from climate change, population growth, and resource constraints.</p> <p>Technology has the potential to make agriculture more efficient, sustainable, and profitable. But it requires entrepreneurs who understand both the technical possibilities and the practical realities of farming. Our experience taught us that successful ag-tech requires deep empathy for farmers and their challenges, not just technical expertise.</p> <h2 id="looking-forward">Looking Forward</h2> <h2 id="the-accountability-moment">The Accountability Moment</h2> <p>As I mentioned in my bio, my co-founder and best friend insisted that I write this story and take “public accountability” for our FarmPlus journey. Consider this me holding up my end of that bargain. Sometimes the best motivation comes from friends who won’t let you forget the wild ideas you’ve pursued together over chai.</p> <p>To anyone reading this who has their own “crazy startup idea” brewing over late-night conversations with friends—don’t just talk about it. Build something, test it, and see where it leads. You might be surprised by what you discover about both the market and yourself along the way.</p> <p><em>What started as an evening conversation over chai turned into a real business, taught us invaluable lessons about entrepreneurship, and opened our eyes to the incredible potential for technology to transform traditional industries. Not bad for a Tuesday night study break.</em></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/WCboys-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/WCboys-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/WCboys-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/WCboys.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure>]]></content><author><name>Adway Kanhere</name></author><category term="non-tech"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[and how an evening chai session with the boys can turn ideas into startups]]></summary></entry></feed>